# 甘肃·临洮
Lintao, Gansu
# 现在雪鱼在临洮 待会呢打算去吃一碗热凉面
Now I’m at Lintao, I will have a bowl of Hot-Cold noodles later.
# 当时注意到热凉面的时候 我就有一个疑问
I was kind of interested when I noticed the name of the Hot-Cold noodles.
# 这个面
# 到底是热的呢还是凉的
Is the noodle hot or cold?
# 查了老半天资料还是觉得一头雾水
I did a lot of research on this one, but still got confused.
# 索性就直接来临洮看一看 热凉面到底是什么样子
Therefore, I thought why not come to this city, and see what is it look like?
# 歌曲：小镇故事多  充满喜和乐
# 进去吃凉面吧
Let’s get in!
# 吃热的还是吃凉的（面条）
Do you want the hot one or the cold one (noodles)?
# 凉的和热的有什么样的区别
What’s the difference between the cold one and the hot one?
# 凉的就是拌了一下油
Cold one is stirred with some oil
# 热的就是直接从锅里捞出来的
Hot one is come right out from the pot
# 那我要热的
Then I want the hot one
# 好的 吃热的
Hot one? Right!
# 要宽面条还是细面条
With the wide noodle or the thin noodle?
# 要细的
The thin one
# 加肉 加肥肠吗
Add meat and pork intestine?
# 加 都加
Yeah, add them all.
# 好的 都加
All of them? Right!
# 辣椒吃吗   可以
Is it okay with hot chili?  Yeah, It’s fine
# 对 加个蛋
Yes, add a braised egg
# 你坐就行
You can have a seat
# 行 行 好 谢谢
Aright, thanks
# 好 谢谢
Thanks
# 不客气
You’re welcome
# 到面馆里吃面 落座之后会上一碗面汤
If you are going to the noodle house, they normally would bring a bowl of noodle soup to your table after you have sat
# 这边一看就是吃面的地方 桌子上摆着蒜
You would know this place is for you to having noodles when you have seen the garlic on the table
# 辣子 还有一壶的醋
With hot chilies, and some vinegar
# 好大一份
It’s huge
# 它这个面条是浸在卤子里的 这个卤子会倒两遍
This noodle is immersed in the braised sauce, they will pour over twice
# 第一遍呢 就是在底下打个底
The first time will put some underneath
# 还要把面条翻一下 让这个面条都有卤子
And flip over the noodles to ensure it is fully covered by the sauce
# 第二个部分呢 就是再倒一勺卤子
Second part will be pouring over the sauce another time
# 这样好再倒上肉啊 鸡蛋这些
And then followed by putting some meat and egg on the top
# 不多说了赶快吃吧 这个面都坨了
I have to start eating as the noodles are going to be soggy
# 我也先拌一拌吧
Mix it first
# 好香啊
Smells good
# 不管面还是肉 都浸满了卤子
Both noodles and meat are fully immersed with the sauce
# 今天是又要了肉 又要了蛋 还是肉蛋双飞的这种类型
Ordered meat and egg in this
# 好喜欢吃辣子下的肉 吃起来香香的
I like to have the meat with some hot chili, so luscious
# 我感觉要的豪华版的 根本就不是来吃面的
I feel like I’m not came here to having these noodles with this deluxe version
# 好像是来吃肉的
Seems in order to having these meats instead
# 面条就像前几天在兰州吃的牛肉面一样
These noodles are just like the beef noodles that I had few days ago in Lanzhou
# 都是这种比较劲道的口感 而且颜色都是淡黄色
They shared the same chewy texture and both in light-yellow color
# 来店里点面 老板的一般问题都是
If you come over to the shop, they will always ask you the same questions
# 要热的 还是要凉的
You want the hot one or the cold one?
# 要宽面还是细面
Wide noodles or thin noodles?
# 要不要肉 要不要辣子
Do you want to add some meat? Are you okay with spicy chili?
# 连环地问 到底吃什么样的面条
Ask you a serial of questions, what do you want specifically?
# 像我这份就是细的面条 热的面条
Like the one I ordered here, this is the hot one and with thin noodles
# 加辣子 加肉 加蛋 全都有了
Add spicy chili, meat, and egg. Added all their selections.
# 这边的调料就是少不了醋 辣子 蒜汁
And vinegar, spicy chili, garlic juice, are indispensable parts of its flavor
# 流水的面馆 铁打的调料 都是这三样
Noodle houses are normally come with these flowed processes and fixed sauces
# 最近吃的都是这三样
I’m having the same flavors lately
# 这碗面最大的特点应该就是这浓郁的卤汁了吧
One of the biggest features of this noodle is the bold taste of its sauce
# 半流淌的状态 让它能够依附于面条
It can attach to the noodles with its semi-liquid state
# 每吃一口 我都要发出吸溜的声音
And I’m making the slurping sound for every single bite
# 吃着吃着就会发现
While in the meantime,
# 卤汁包裹下的面条 味道好像更饱满一些
You will find out the sauce wrapped noodles will become more flavorful
# 吃完了热凉面呢  我打算去他们的厨房看一看
After finished this noodle, I’m going to have a look in their kitchen
# 因为我感觉里面的气氛好像是异常火爆
Cause I feel like it’s so hearty in there
# 正好借这个机会看一看
With this chance, I’m going to checkout
# 凉面（还有热凉面）是怎么做成的吧
How they make the hot-cold noodles
# 走进厨房 首先能够看到的是他们切肉的场景
First, you will see they are cutting the meat after you walked into the kitchen
# 在这边倒是没有看到大刀剁肉 这种酣畅淋漓的场面
You won’t see they are chopping the meat exuberantly with heavy knifes
# 反而是这种三角小刀片肉的场面倒是别具一格
Instead, they are using this little triangular blade to slice the meat.
# 肉切到什么程度
How thin do you have to cut this meat to?
# 要切的很薄很薄
Very thin
# 这样的厚度就刚刚好
Like this one
# 这边放在面里的肉 不仅有肘子肉 还有卤肥肠
The meat they are offering are not limited to pork shoulder, but also braised pork intestine
# 在卤肉的旁边 就是一小碟 一小碟的卤肥肠
Beside the pork shoulder, there have putted pork intestine into each single small plate
# 肉是提前做出来的 切出来会比较干
Since the meat is cooked already a while ago, and a bit of dry when you cut it
# 所以说 切过的肉 还要在后面的大锅里再冒（烫）一下
Therefore, the sliced meats are going to quick boil for a moment
# 出锅的时候 还会再放一些老汤
They will put some broth in it when it come out from the pot
# 这样会让肉更有味道
Then the meat will become more flavorful
# 再朝前走 就是他们做面的地方了
And a few steps further, that’s the place where they produce the noodles
# 凉面店里的面条呢 也是像兰州牛肉面一样
The noodles in this shop are pretty like the Lanzhou beef noodles
# 需要现场拉出来
They need stretch the dough in the same time
# 根据顾客的需求 有的会要粗一点的 有的会要细一点的
Followed by the customer’s requirements, someone would order the thick one, others may want the thin one
# 都是根据需求 现做出来的
It’s all made out after their requests
# 临洮有句关于做凉面的话就是
There is a saying about Lintao’s Hot-Cold noodles
# 这个面需要  三遍水 三遍蓬灰 九九八十一道揉
This noodle need go through many processes
# 就是为了让这个面拉起来更有韧性 吃起来是劲道
To ensure the noodles will be more chewy
# 小哥 你这个面揉的像麻花一样
Hey, your dough is like Mahua when you are kneading
# 一定要这么用力地揉吗
Do you have to kneading this hard?
# 对 对
Yeah
# 揉得越厉害 它越筋道
The harder you knead the dough, the stronger it will get
# 这一块面团要揉多久
How long should you knead this dough for?
# 半个小时吧
Around half hour
# 小哥 这个过程叫溜条 还是叫溜条
# —
# 、
Is the word Liu pronounced with first tone or fourth tone?
# 叫溜条
# —
First tone
# 就是把面团揪成一块块的
Just need to pull this dough into pieces
# 这一块就是一碗面
One piece per serving
# 一个剂子是一碗面
One piece is a bowl of noodles
# 大小是一样的
The size is same
# 后面这个拉面的小哥很有意思
The guy who are pulling the dough is kind of interesting
# 他刚才把面条丢进锅里 然后冲着我说
He just throws the noodles into the pot and saying to me
# 这个东西很简单
This thing is very easy
# 我们过去看看真的是这么简单吗
Let’s see how easy that could be
# 我动作稍微慢一点 让你看清楚
I will move slowly, and you can have a clear look
# 小哥 你说做拉面简单吗
You said it’s very easy to make pulled noodles?
# 简单  非常简单
It’s very simple
# 小姐姐 我想问一下 凉面还有热凉面的区别
Hey, Miss. I want asking what’s the difference between cold noodles and hot-cold noodles?
# 凉面就是 面从锅里捞出来 再用油拌一下
Cold noodles are made directly from the pot and mixed up with some oil
# 晾凉了 就是凉面
Wait it’s getting cold, then it will be cold noodles
# 热面就是面直接从锅里捞出来 直接调上汤汁 就是热的
Hot noodles are the same but pouring over some broth and sauce when it come out from the pot.
# 不用拌凉
You don’t need to wait it getting cold and mixing with the oil
# 就是这样的
That’s it
# 我看咱们这边吃面条是分宽的和细的
You can order the noodles in different shape of forms beside wide and thin
# 还有二细 韭叶 三细
There are Erxi, Jiuye, Sanxi
# 那顾客是要细的多一些呢 还是要粗的多一些呢
The degree of thinness and thickness will depend on
# 这个就看个人口味了
Personal favors
# 有的人喜欢吃宽的 有的人喜欢吃细的
Someone may like the wide one, someone like the thin one
# 好 谢谢
Alright, thinks
# 不用谢
You’re welcome
# 刚才小姐姐说的是
The miss just said
# 凉面和热凉面在做法和操作上的区别
The distinctions of method and how to handle between cold noodles and hot-cold noodles
# 就是热凉面不经过拌油冷却这个过程
It’s hot-cold noodles are not required of having the processes of mixing with the oil and wait it become cold
# 实际上 最先出现的是凉面
In fact, cold noodles are the original one
# 那个时候都是挑着担子在外面卖
People used to sell the cold noodles outside by carrying around them with Danzi
# 担子的一边的放的是已经用油拌好的凉面
The one side of Danzi is filled with oil mixed cold noodles
# 另一边呢 放的是热汤
And the other side is filled with the hot broth
# 后来呢 有了凉面店
And later, there’s cold noodle house
# 有的顾客说可以把面直接放在热卤里
And some customers said the noodles can be put into the gravy
# 这么吃就是胃舒服些
And the stomach will feel a bit more comfortable
# 这个时候 热凉面才开始出现
At that time, Hot-Cold noodles began to appear
# 这么看来 热凉面应该是凉面发展的产物吧
Seems the hot-cold noodles should be the product of cold noodles development in this way
# 还有一点就是
And there is another point
# 吃凉面和吃热凉面 和季节有很大的关系
The seasonality is also mostly related of choosing cold noodles and hot-cold noodles
# 像这种天气 来碗凉面 可能更配一些
A bowl of cold noodles will be more fitted in these days
# 奶奶 吃面之前要先剥蒜吗
Hi Miss, do you have to peel the garlic before you having the noodles?
# 这个蒜
This garlic
# 吃这个蒜配面里面的肉
Eat this garlic with the meat from the noodles
# 奶奶 您经常来吃凉面吗
Hi Miss, do you come to here all the time?
# 经常吃
Yeah, very often
# 他们家的凉面 就是好
Their cold noodles are very good
# 凉面是咱们这边特色是吧
Cold noodles are the specialty of here?
# 临洮的特色面
Lintao’s special noodles
# 您点的是热凉面还是凉面呢
Did you order the hot-cold noodles or the cold noodles?
# 凉的 它那个汤不是热的吗
Cold one, but the broth is still hot?
# 夏天吃这个好
It’s good of having this one in the summer
# 在临洮 满大街的都是凉面店
There are full of cold noodle houses in Lintao
# 凉面呢 大家从早上起来就可以吃
Everyone can have the cold noodles right start from the day
# 一直到下午两点
Until two o’clock in the afternoon
# 早上呢 不需要点那么贵的 不需要加那么多的肉
In the morning, you don’t have to order this much amount of meat
# 一种肉 或者说加一个蛋 已经足够了
One type of meat or a braised egg should be enough
# 我的这种 我觉得加的 有点过分了
The one that I had is bit of too much
# 好了 今天的视频就到这
Aright, today’s video will be stop right here
# ~~拜拜
~~Bye
# 关  注
雪 鱼 探 店